Guide to the Lewis Hine Fellowship Photographs Collection, 2003-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lewis Hine Fellowship photographs collection 2003-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies.
2.5 linear feet Extent: 157 Items
The Lewis Hine Documentary Fellows Program (LHDFP) is administered by the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University to support documentary photographers who address humanitarian issues in the U.S. and abroad. The Lewis Hine Fellowship Photographs Collection represents a selection of images from the documentary projects of six LHDFP fellows: Alex Fattal, Maital Guttman, Kate Joyce, Elena Rue, Amanda van Scoyoc, and Lucy Wilson. The photographic images and videos in the collection depict home and community life of disadvantaged families and children in several sub-Saharan African nations (South Africa, Zimbabwe, and Ethiopia), as well as Boston, Massachusetts. They show everyday life and activities, such as children playing and completing chores, mothers cooking meals, disabled children going to school, household living conditions, and impoverished orphans and HIV-positive children in their familial situations, as well as funerals and school presentations (among other community events). In addition to photographic prints, there are also some documents relating to the projects, and DVDs of the photographers' documentary work. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
RL.00811
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Lewis Hine Documentary Fellowship Photographs Collection were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from 2008-2010.
Biographical Note
The Lewis Hine Documentary Fellows Program (LHDFP) is administered by the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University to support documentary photographers who address humanitarian issues in the U.S. and abroad. The LHDFP is the first postgraduate program at Duke University's Center for Documentary Studies (CDS), and is part of a long-standing commitment to youth-focused work at the CDS. In order to work toward fulfilling this commitment, LHDFP places Fellows with organizations seeking creative solutions to the specific problems faced by women, adolescents, and children in poor, marginalized areas. Each year, Hines Fellows work with local organizations to document their chosen topic over the course of ten months. They then return to work with documentarians on their projects. Hine Fellows, selected each spring, are graduates of Duke University, the Robertson Scholars program between Duke and the University of North Carolina-Chapel Hill, or of the Continuing Studies Certificate Program at the CDS. The Lewis Hine Documentary Fellows Program is supported by The Philanthropic Initiative and the Jessica Jennifer Cohen Foundation.
Biographical Notes for Photographers in Collection
(Biographies are from the Center for Documentary Studies web site)
Alex Fattal
Alex Fattal graduated from Duke in 2001 with a B.A. in comparative area studies. Alex is a photographer who has made images of rural family life in Russia, Cuba, and most recently, in Colombia on a Fulbright Fellowship. During his time in Colombia, Alex also collaborated with local NGOs on programming related to issues of sustainable development and children's rights. He spent he time as a Fellow in Durban, South Africa, where he worked with a local NGO in its efforts for children's rights advocacy. As part of his work there, he developed the body of work contained within this collection, entitled: Images of Childhood in South Africa Ten Years after Apartheid.
Maital Guttman
Maital Guttman is a documentary filmmaker. As a freshman at Duke University her interest in documentary work began through the Humanitarian Challenges at Home and Abroad FOCUS Program. During her senior year she produced her first full-length documentary titled Mechina: A Preparation. The film follows six Israeli teens three months before they become soldiers, and sheds light on Israeli society in a way that reaches beyond general images of conflict. As a Lewis Hine Fellow, Guttman worked with an NGO in Nekkie, South Africa, and documented the stories of children that attend an arts-based HIV education center in South Africa.
Kate Joyce
Kate Joyce studied sociology and photojournalism at San Francisco State University and, during fall 2003, worked on her Certificate in Documentary Studies through the Center for Documentary Studies. Kate is a photographer interested in the relationship between documentary processes and art. She spent seven months photographing in Chile, where she focused on female-headed households. Her fellowship project was spent in Bloemfontein, South Africa, photographing the body of work known as Site Insight: Mapping Grassland Phase II, and working on documentary projects with a local NGO (DEDI) that focuses on early childhood education and parental-empowerment in rural and informal settlements. She has also photographed in Iceland, Guatemala, Spain, and the American West.
Elena Rue
Elena Rue is a 2003 graduate of Kenyon College, where she studied anthropology and photography. During an intensive semester at the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University (CDS) in 2001, she completed a number of undergraduate documentary studies courses and was involved with CDS’s Youth Document Durham program and Student Action with Farmworkers, an organization housed at CDS. She spent that following spring semester in Ghana documenting the unique sign language of the isolated deaf community of Adamorobe. Rue spent nine months as a Fellow in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia working with an NGO that supports children whose families have been affected by HIV. The project she developed while working with these families is called Love After Loss.
Amanda van Scoyoc
Amanda van Scoyoc graduated from the University of Pennsylvania in 2005 with a B.A. in psychology and a minor in fine arts. For the last six years, she has worked on a variety of documentary projects, including a series of photographs, interviews, and writings about the impact that adopting nine-year-old Russian twin sisters has had on her family as well as on their own adjustment and development. She has also volunteered as a photographer with two nonprofits in Guatemala and Honduras, and worked as an art teacher at a Boy's Club of America, where she has incorporated journaling into her teaching. As a Fellow, van Scoyoc worked with an NGO in Chelsea, Mass. that helps at-risk youth become self-sufficient, responsible citizens. Her project regarding low-income and teenage mothers is entitled: Raising Them Right: Young Motherhood in Chelsea, Massachusetts.
Lucy Wilson
Lucy Wilson graduated from Duke in 2001 with a major in public policy studies. After graduation, Lucy lived in Ghana, where she worked for the United States Refugee Resettlement Program - Overseas Processing Entity (OPE), interviewing refugees throughout West Africa and leading circuit rides for the OPE field team. While at Duke, Lucy initiated Teaching Together, Learning Together, a partnership between Duke professors and Durham public school teachers. She was also a research assistant with CARE's Office of Public Policy and Governmental Relations, where she worked on a public advocacy campaign to increase international family-planning funding. As part of her coursework at the Center for Documentary Studies, she photographed a Nigerian family living in Chapel Hill, North Carolina. Wilson's project as a Fellow (The Highfield District of Harare, Zimbabwe) reflects her time with the NGO Child Protection Society (CPS), a local child rights advocacy organization in Zimbabwe.
Collection Overview
The Lewis Hine Fellowship Photographs Collection spans the years 2003-2008 and consists of selected images from the documentary collections of six of the Lewis Hine Documentary Fellows Program (LHDFP) fellows in the following locations: Alex Fattal (South Africa); Maital Guttman (South Africa); Kate Joyce (South Africa); Elena Rue (Ethiopia); Amanda van Scoyoc (Boston, Mass.); and Lucy Wilson (Zimbabwe). The photographic images and videos in the collection depict home and community life of disadvantaged and displaced families and children in several sub-Saharan African nations, as well as people in the communities of Chelsea and Boston, Massachusetts. Images show everyday life and activities, such as children playing and completing chores, mothers cooking meals, disabled children going to school, household living conditions, and impoverished orphans and HIV-positive children in their familial situations, as well as funerals and school presentations (among other community events). Several series reveal the after-effects of displacement and social conditions in post-apartheid South Africa (Kwazulu-Natal and Bloemfontein). Two of the photographers' projects also include black-and-white images taken by the children and their families, along with quotes from those individuals regarding the images.
The collection consists of 147 color and black-and-white unmatted prints, ranging in size from 6.5x10 inches to 13x20 inches. There are also 4 DVDs containing both still- and moving-image documentaries with text and audio interviews. Several of the projects include paper copies of the introductions to the bodies of work, as well as full captions for the photographs. Many of the photographs are also available as digital images currently mounted on the LHDFP section of the CDS website.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Collection Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by photographer, whose bodies of works are then arranged in original order as identified by the photographer.
Subject Headings
Fattal, Alex; Guttman, Maital; Joyce, Katie; Rue, Elena; Van Scoyoc, Amanda; Wilson, Lucy; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies; Blacks -- Relocation -- South Africa -- KwaZulu-Natal; Children -- South Africa -- Pictorial works; Children -- Zimbabwe -- Social conditions; Children's rights -- Africa, Sub-Saharan; Disabled children -- education; HIV infections -- Social aspects -- Africa; HIV-positive children; Nongovernmental organizations -- Social aspects; Orphans -- Africa, Sub-Saharan -- Social conditions; Orphans -- Ethiopia -- Addis Ababa -- Social conditions; Poor children -- Massachusetts -- Boston -- Social conditions; Post-apartheid era -- Kwazulu (South Africa); Bloemfontein (South Africa) -- Social conditions; Chelsea (Mass.) -- Social life and customs -- Pictorial works; Ethiopia -- Social conditions -- 21st century -- Pictorial works; South Africa -- Social conditions -- Pictorial works; Zimbabwe -- Pictorial works; Zimbabwe -- Social conditions; Documentary films; Documentary photography; Documentary photography -- South Africa; Black-and-white photographs; Color photographs; DVDs
Detailed Description of Collection
- Alex Fattal Photographs Series, 2003-2004, (1 box)
  As a 2002-2003 Lewis Hine Documentary Fellow, Fattal became a documentary researcher for the Children's Rights Centre (CRC) in Durban, South Africa from February 2003 to August 2004. The CRC, initially a peace building organization during the violence in KwaZulu-Natal in the 1980s and early 1990s, has grown into a national non-governmental organization mobilizing and advocating for children's rights in every sector of South African society. Fattal's assignment was to explore challenges to children's rights in a qualitative, visual and participatory way, which he undertook over sixteen months by way of traveling to and stay with various households. While staying with these families, he worked with the children leading a series of discussions about photographs in their everyday environment and taught them the basics of framing, lighting, and operating a camera (which they then taught to their family members). Fattal's project (entitled Images of Childhood in South Africa Ten Years after Apartheid) consists of photographs in color that he took, and photographs in black and white that children and their parents or caregivers took. Various family members would tell stories about the images they would make, and these narratives are included below with the captions. (Note: all names and specific locations have been changed by Fattal.)
  Twenty-nine color images and twelve black-and-white images on 8.5 x 11" Epson paper. Captions taken from original texts.
  - Paper copy of introduction and captions, 2004, (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Color Prints Subseries, 2003-2004
    - Running around tree (Box 1, Image 01)
      Children of a family in the Metlagole, North West.
    - Classroom scene of interracial/disabled school (Box 1, Image 02)
      School with special services for children with disabilities in Ramfontein, Free State.
    - Songwa and Wilo in market, refugees with shoes in foreground (Box 1, Image 03)
      Children from a refugee family Sunday at market in Baldwin, Kwa Zulu-Natal.
    - Boy pulling mules carrying water (Box 1, Image 04)
      Fetching water from rivers running through an asbestos-laden dam in Ag-Thabane, Limpopo.
    - Going to school on tractor (Box 1, Image 05)
      Children of farm laborers on the way to school in Hirsenbosch, Western Cape.
    - Dishing out food for 13 (Box 1, Image 06)
      Preparing to serve dinner for thirteen, nine children, five adopted from sisters who have passed away in Unkunkulu, Kwa Zulu-Natal.
    - Woman with baby behind curtain (Box 1, Image 07)
      HIV+ mother with her baby Hauperville, Kwa Zulu-Natal.
    - Morning preparations, combing and dressing (Box 1, Image 08)
      Preparing for school in Unkunkulu, Kwa Zulu-Natal.
    - Two girls at Hindi temple (Box 1, Image 09)
      Sisters playing at Hindi temple in Baldwin, Kwa Zulu-Natal.
    - Playing rock game with wig (Box 1, Image 10)
      San children at play in Vleifontein, Northern Cape.
    - Muslim prayer (Box 1, Image 11)
      Children performing afternoon Du'as in Baldwin, Kwa Zulu-Natal.
    - Justine and Yolanda cuddle (Box 1, Image 12)
      Children of farm laborers in Hirsenbosch, Western Cape.
    - Handing baby from back of boy to hand of woman (Box 1, Image 13)
      Family in Metlagole, North West (Note: within the old homeland of Boputatswana).
    - Men sitting on red stools with backs to camera (Box 1, Image 14)
      Unemployed in Unkunkulu, Kwa Zulu-Natal.
    - Confrontation at Kids Haven with tie (Box 1, Image 15)
      In a shelter for neglected and abused children in Wanoni, Gauteng.
    - Disabled children portrait in front of sandbox (Box 1, Image 16)
      Morning playtime in Ramfontein, Free State.
    - Watching soccer taken from behind (Box 1, Image 17)
      Watching a soccer match in Vleifontein, Northern Cape.
    - Girl in pink skirt carrying younger boy (Box 1, Image 18)
      In Vleifontein, Northern Cape.
    - Kids with aqua bowls at sunset (Box 1, Image 19)
      Late afternoon in Unkunkulu, Kwa Zulu-Natal.
    - Ironing with coils on ground (Box 1, Image 20)
      Ironing and keeping warm in Unkunkulu, Kwa Zulu-Natal.
    - Being bad in Limpopo (Box 1, Image 21)
      Being mischievous in Ag-Thabane, Limpopo.
    - Old man sitting in mealies, corn (Box 1, Image 22)
      Grandfather resting in Vleifontein, Northern Cape.
    - Slingshot (Box 1, Image 23)
    - Soccer, header (Box 1, Image 24)
    - Playing card despondent (Box 1, Image 25)
      Orphaned children in Hauperville, Kwa Zulu-Natal.
    - Church music in house (Box 1, Image 26)
      Church at a neighbor's home in Hirsenbosch, Western Cape.
    - Michele watching TV happily (Box 1, Image 27)
      Watching cartoons in Baldwin, Kwa Zulu-Natal.
    - Tshepo and young boy portrait (Box 1, Image 28)
      In shelter for neglected and abused children in Wanoni, Gauteng.
    - Tent, dramatic sky (Box 1, Image 29)
      Scottsdrift, Northern Cape.
    - Smiling in doorway (Box 1, Image 30)
      Metlagole, North West.
  - Black and White Prints Subseries, 2003-2004
    Made by children, as well as parents and caregivers, with narrated captions.
    - Girl squatting extending arms; Location: Baldwin, Kwa Zulu-Natal; Photo by: Father (Box 1, Image 1)
      I have a sister her name is Furaha, she was born in South Africa. Actually she has never been to Burundi from the time she was born until now. She is two years already. She'd like to go to Burundi and visit her grandmother and uncle and people who know us from the time we were in Burundi. I think even Gerard and Jacques can't remember Burundi very well because they left the time they were kids. I think they don't know anything about the war there because they were young. I don't know. - Wawa, 15 years old.
    - Cooking on ground; Location: Vleifontein, Northern Cape; Photo by: Father (Box 1, Image 2)
      I can't explain what [Katolo] tastes like, you can taste for yourself, it grows wild. It comes from Namibia and is part of our staple diet. You can eat it with pap or other food but if you really want to enjoy it you must have it with meat. - Father.
    - Tall building; Location: Wanoni, Gauteng; Photo by: Marlene, 15 years old (Box 1, Image 3)
      It reminds me of the time I ran away from home and came to Gauteng. I was around these huge buildings and I was so frightened, just to look at the buildings. I was so scared I didn't know where to go. I was just crying all the way and people were just staring at me. I was so frightened. Then I thought, maybe I should go and sit where there are no buildings and lots of people around, so I went to this place over here. I was sitting over there and it was so quiet but still I was crying. When these big men would just pass I was so scared, I just thought that maybe one would come and rape me. I just thought something bad can happen to me. But I just sat there until the other girl who I was with said we must take another walk. - Marlene, 15 years old.
    - Two houses, tent and cinderblock, people hanging outside; Location: Vleifontein, Northern Cape; Photo by: Father (Box 1, Image 4)
      In Vleifontein we now have taps and don't fetch water from the river. Because we are becoming modernised we now have to pay for water. It is going to be difficult since many people are unemployed and do not have an income to pay for water. - Father.
    - Tug of war; Location: Wanoni, Gauteng; Photo by: Thomas, 12 years old (Box 1, Image 5)
      Tug of war.
    - Bending over ball; Location: Metlagole, North West; Photo by: Mom (Box 1, Image 6)
      Willem started getting therapy from the age of around three months, six months something around there...He's still keeping on with his therapy. He gets therapy twice a week from school, he has improved a lot. - Mom.
    - Walking under arm, protection; Location: Hauperville, Kwa Zulu-Natal; Photo by: Sicelo, 5 years old (Box 1, Image 7)
      When we were playing we stayed close so if [our mother] called us we would hear her because she was sick. Me and Lungile were discussing that, and how our mother was important to us. She helped us get what we wanted at school. - Nikiwe, 11 years old.
    - Portrait with magazine of white girl with baby; Location: Hauperville, Kwa Zulu-Natal; Photo by: Nikiwe, 11 years old (Box 1, Image 8)
      I'd like to be very famous and have money. - Nikiwe, 11 years old.
    - Baby photographed outside in middle of the frame; Location: Metlagole, North West; Photo by: Pule, 9 years old (Box 1, Image 9)
      Baby's portrait.
    - Hold up; Location: Hauperville, Kwa Zulu-Natal; Photo by: Sicelo, 5 years old (Box 1, Image 10)
      If I go to school that's good because there is no future without education. I want to train to become a policewoman, not just become one. I'd like me and my sisters to be successful and admirable in our community, to be able to help other people like we were helped to be educated. - Gcina, 17 years old.
    - Devout pose; Location: Baldwin, Kwa Zulu-Natal; Photo by: Salumu, 14 years old (Box 1, Image 11)
      This is my older brother Wawa he wants to be a musician in his life, his favorite musician is Tupac. He calls himself Tupac whatever he's doing. Even in this picture he posed like Tupac. If you know Tupac you will see how it resembles Tupac. Everything is Tupac, Tupac, Tupac...In this picture he's dressed pocket down and calls himself a nigga. In every part of his life he wants to be like Tupac. - Salumu, 14 years old.
    - Sunspot; Location: Hirsenbosch, Western Cape; Photo by: Mother (Box 1, Image 12)
      Vineyard workers.
- Maital Guttman Documentary Series, 2005-2006, (1 box)
  As a Lewis Hine Fellow, Guttman spent the 2005-2006 academic year working with the 10 Million Memory Project (10MMP), which is supported by the Regional Psycho-Social Support Initiative (REPSSI) and its partners. The purpose of these non-governmental organizations is to provide a therapeutic approach to healing psychological wounds in the southern region of Africa by way of creating safe spaces for children to share their memories and tell their life stories. More specifically, REPSSI is a non-profit regional organization that works to lessen the social and emotional effects of HIV and AIDS, poverty, and conflict among children and youth in thirteen countries in East and Southern Africa. Guttman was sent to Nekkie, South Africa to work with MADaboutART, an arts-based HIV education and youth empowerment program that is affiliated with 10MMP and REPSSI. While there, Guttman filmed a documentary entitled Three in a Million: a hero book story. She also aided in the filming of a short drama developed by the students at MADaboutART (Broken) and a short film about the students' efforts to clean up their community (Gardening Eden). Her project as a whole is entitled: Breaking the Silence.
  This collection includes two DVDs that include a documentary film and two short films.
  [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.]
  - DVD: Broken and Gardening Eden, 2005-2006 (Box 2)
    Broken is a short drama created by the students of MADaboutART that brings to light the issue of incestuous rape and family stigma against children in their community. Gardening Eden is a short film that documents the understanding of the importance of caring for the environment, as well as the efforts of the students at MADaboutART to reduce and clean up garbage dumping within their community. Each short film has a running time of approximately four minutes.
  - DVD: Three in a Million: a Hero Book Story, 2005-2006 (Box 2)